Justin Bieber, Muhammad Ali, Miley
Cyrus. And then there's murderers,
rapists, arsonists. I probably have seen
more brains than anybody in the world.
And now, your brain. So, this is going
to be really hard for you. You have
ADHD. Really? Dr. Daniel Amen, the
world's leading expert
on the brain.
Dr. Amen's mission is to end mental
illness
by creating a revolution in brain
health. Buckle up, Dr. Amen. Let me know
what you see. Your brain is involved in
everything you do. And after today, you
will always care about your brain. What
things make the brain worse? Drugs,
alcohol, not getting good sleep, sugar,
fruit juice, hitting a soccer ball with
your head, caffeine. Caffeine? It
shrinks it. What's bad about sugar?
You're more likely to get an obesity.
And as your weight goes up, the actual
physical size and function of your brain
goes down. That should scare the fat off
anyone. And then there's social media.
If you're on 3 and 1/2 hours a day, you
begin to wear out those pleasure centers
that bring you happiness and they bring
you pleasure and they bring you drive.
You thrill them to death. But, you're
not stuck with the brain you have. You
can make it better. I can prove it. So,
it starts with
Let's look at my brain. Let's do this.
We have evidence of And that's normal in
our society. The problem is two or three
of those can impact the rest of your
life and nobody knows about it.
Quick one. This is really, really
fascinating to me. On the back end of
our YouTube channel, it says that 69.9%
of you that watch this channel
frequently over the lifetime of this
channel haven't yet hit the subscribe
button. I just wanted to ask you a
favor. It helps this channel so much if
you choose to just subscribe. Helps us
scale the guests, helps us scale the
production, and it makes the show
bigger. So, if I could ask you for one
favor, if you've watched this show
before and you've enjoyed it and you
like this episode that you're currently
watching, could you please hit the
subscribe button? Thank you so much and
I will repay that gesture by making sure
that everything we do here gets better
and better and better and better. That
is a promise I'm willing to make you. Do
we have a deal?
Dr. Amen,
if someone's just clicked on this
podcast
and they're considering sticking around
or maybe doing something else with their
time.
Can you explain to me
based on what you know that we're going
to be discussing and the subject matter
we're going to be discussing and how
important it is,
the benefit to their life if they stick
around?
10 extra years of cognitive performance
in their life,
better love, better money,
better health, because your brain, we're
going to talk about, is involved in
everything you do. How you think, how
you feel, how you act, how you get along
with other people. And my goal is to
end, this is going to sound huge and it
is,
and it's going to sound impossible, but
it's not. My goal is to end mental
illness
by
creating
a revolution in brain health. I hate the
term mental illness. It shames people.
It's stigmatizing and it's wrong. These
things aren't mental disorders, they're
brain disorders. If you get your brain
healthy, well, your mind tends to
follow. So, you're depressed, an
antidepressant is not doing one thing
for getting your brain healthy. Nobody's
talking to you about your diet, your
level of exercise, your sleep, not
living in a mold-filled home, not really
allowing your kids hit soccer balls with
their head, right? Cuz that's not brain
healthy.
And if we can create this revolution in
brain health,
the incidence of mental health disorders
will go down
by half.
And I guess that's part of the reveal
here is you've actually scanned
my brain. And you're going to tell me
today the results that
you have on your laptop over there in
the corner of the room. So, I came to
your clinic in Los Angeles, and they
made me do a test on a computer. Like it
was almost like a speed test of sorts.
And then they made me lie down in a big
machine
for about How long was that? About 30
minutes? 15 minutes.
15 minutes?
While this big machine rotated around my
head and looked at my brain. That was my
experience of what happened. And then I
filled out some questionnaires about
myself and my brain and my life
generally.
And from that,
all that data feeds into the thing
you're about to show me now.
Yes. So, I never will make a diagnosis
from a scan. Okay. I make a diagnosis
from all the information, which is why
we had you fill out all that information
and I gave you a test called the Conners
Continuous Performance Test, which is a
15-minute test of attention. And every
time you see a a letter, you hit the
spacebar,
except when you see the the letter X.
When you see the letter X, you don't do
anything. So, it measures impulse
control and inhibition, response time.
And you actually did fine
on the test.
And but there's other
evidence that you might in fact have ADD
or ADHD from
getting bored easily to poor
handwriting, being disorganized,
and so on. Uh Uh and obviously you're
very bright but
struggled a bit in school. So,
with all that information,
um first thing to do is look at a
healthy scan so we know what a healthy
scan
looks like.
And we're going to show it in two
different ways. We're going to look at
the outside surface
of your brain. So, a healthy one is the
image
on the left and all we should see is
full, even, symmetrical activity. So,
the image on the top left is looking
underneath the brain. So, the top is the
front part of the brain, the bottom is
the back, the top is an area called the
prefrontal cortex, hugely important in
humans, largest in humans than any other
animal by far. It's 30% of the human
brain, 11% of the chimpanzee brain. And
then the back is the cerebellum, back
bottom part of the brain.
Um again, very important, involved in
processing speed.
The bottom right of the images on the
left is looking down from the top. Uh
the other two looking at the brain from
the side. Color doesn't matter, it's the
shape. It should be
full, even, and symmetrical.
The images on the right, the color
matters. So, it's what we call our
active images. Blue is average activity,
red is the top 15%,
white is the top 8%. And you see all the
white. So, the white is where things are
really happening. It's really hot. Okay.
And that's healthy. That's normal. And
that's going to become very important
for you. So, if we look at your brain,
it's a little bumpy, and so I'll ask you
about toxins. Are there anything toxic
in your life? What What are all toxins?
So, think alcohol, marijuana,
mold, uh
heavy metals in your body, infections,
and so if it's not
alcohol or drugs, then I begin to go,
"Have you ever lived in a mold-filled
environment? Maybe we should test you
for that. Do you have more mercury in
your body or lead in your body than you
should?" So, for example, I had very
high mercury levels. My brain sort of
looked like that when I first scanned
it. It was toxic. And I had very high
mercury levels. Like, I never drank.
I just don't like it. Never smoked.
Never did drugs. But, my brain looked
toxic. And so, you then have to go hunt
down, "Well, why?"
And for me, it was mercury.
Um decreased activity in your left
prefrontal cortex. So, when I think of
maybe ADD-like symptoms in your life,
probably coming from there.
And decreased activity in your left
temporal lobe.
And you right-handed? Yeah. Yeah. So,
that can go with the irritability. What
I've seen is that can go with sort of
short fuse. Mhm. And your prefrontal
cortex is sort of the brain's
supervisor. It watches you.
And your prefrontal cortex is flat. Mhm.
And I don't like that. And then when I
heard you played soccer or when I read
you played soccer, it's very common in
my soccer players. Now, how long did you
play soccer for? Uh, pretty much all of
my childhood.
And any concussions playing soccer? I
think I had a couple of big head bangs
that
were significant, but not many. Not
nothing that took me to hospital, but I
had a couple of moments where I was
pulled off the pitch because like there
was a clash of heads.
So.
Your brain is soft, about the
consistency of soft butter.
Your skull is really hard and has sharp
bony ridges.
Um.
Two or three of those can impact the
rest of your life and nobody knows about
it.
Because nobody looks. Right? If you went
in saw a thousand psychiatrists, say, "I
want to focus better and
have better temper."
You saw a thousand psychiatrists, two of
them would look at your brain, which I
think is
insane.
So, the colors here that I'm looking at,
the What does the the red and the green
So, the color really Doesn't matter
here. doesn't matter. It's the shape.
So, when I see this hole, you don't have
holes in your brain. What the hole means
is less blood flow than is optimal. In
fact, I'm going to show you
if you do what I ask you to do
and we scan you
6 months from now, that'll be better. I
have a program that tells me
if you do what I ask you to do, this is
what's generally going to happen. And if
you don't do what I ask you to do, well,
this is what it's going to look like 5
years from now, 10 years from now. And
you're young. If you
get serious about loving and repairing
your brain,
your 60s, 70s, 80s are going to be
amazing because you're going to have a
healthy brain. If you go, "Oh, Amen's a
quack and I don't believe any of this
crap."
it's going to be really hard for you
because you're not going to have full
access to your brain.
And that's scary. So, I know that's sort
of a big deal, but I think this is
from
traumatic brain injury at some point
and a bit of a toxin, which may be mold.
Mhm.
And then when I say mold, our house was
very, very dirty growing up.
So,
that's what I assume you're speaking to
that. And we did have like mold around
the window sill sometimes and we had
mice and
rats at some point and
it was like living in a house that a
hoarder
had uh
lived in because some of the rooms were
just stacked to the ceiling with crap.
So,
I think maybe if you're talking about
mold or a toxic brain, I I I'm guessing
that's where it's come from.
If that makes
it gets in your body, unless you do
something active to get it out, it
stays. I really and can continue to
cause problems. And then if we go to the
active scan,
it's very different than I want it to
be.
And I know I can make it better. But if
we go back to
what's healthy,
lots of activity in the cerebellum,
your cerebellum
is sleepy
despite you probably being very
coordinated. I need to activate that
thing. It's really important to get
better activity
there. And you have this diamond
pattern. So, you have ADD and we'll talk
more about it. It's a subtype I call
overfocused ADD where you can be
obsessive when you're really interested
in something, but if it doesn't interest
you,
it's hard for you to focus.
So,
if you look at this, it looks like a
diamond. And when I see that diamond,
I think of past emotional trauma.
And uh I published a big study
looking at this 20,000 people, can I
separate emotional trauma from physical
trauma? And I can with actually high
levels of accuracy, and it looks to me
like there's sort of bit of both
for you. Do you play racket sports?
No, I don't.
So, that'll be one of my prescriptions
for you. And actually, study from
England, people play racket sports live
longer than everybody else by far.
Soccer was on the bottom, like soccer
and football were on the bottom, but
tennis, table tennis, racket ball, now
pickle ball,
uh badminton are on the top.
But let's talk about this diamond for a
bit. When I say emotional trauma, Mhm.
what comes up for you? So, a few things.
The first thing is my parents were
always at war. Growing up as a kid in a
household where there was so much
screaming and negative energy, but then
growing up with shame because we was I
was so different from everyone else
around me.
Never inviting friends back to my house
in those 16 years that I lived there
before I left, so nobody really knew
where I lived either. I think of all
that stuff when I think about like
emotional trauma.
Well, that's a lot. Okay. Yeah.
I mean, if you grow up in a stressful
environment, boo,
and um a hostile environment where your
parents are at war,
it trains your brain,
your emotional brain to become
hyperactive, Mhm. because you always
have to watch
for danger.
And
that gets programmed early.
And even later,
when there's not the danger, your body
still can look for Mhm. You're waiting
for that
next bad thing
to happen.
And Do you think I have ADHD? I do.
Now, the question would be,
who has it in your family? Cuz it
doesn't just show up. But often,
children who have ADHD have one or both
parents who have it. And you can see
those similar traits.
And
it sounds like one or both of your
parents could have been a little bit
conflict seeking.
My My mother.
And if I was to hazard a guess at which
one of my parents had ADHD, and this is
just me guessing, not trying to diagnose
my parents, I would say it's would have
been my mother.
Why?
She's the She's the most irritable.
Handwriting isn't great. She
is
a little bit more sort of like
scat scattered, I should say.
She's a lot more messy. My dad's like
very organized with everything. My mom's
very very very messy. Like me. Um
The The other thing I would ask is,
what did teachers say about you?
I went back to speak at my school
to the GCSE and A-level students. I've
done it twice. And I remember one of the
teachers came up to me. Bearing in mind
at this age, I'm 24, 25 years old. And
she said, "You are a useless student,
but you are nice. You're a nice person."
I was never swearing or throwing chairs,
but I was useless. And I spent most of
the time in the exclusion unit, which is
where you go if you don't do your
homework or you don't attend. I just
couldn't sit in classrooms. I couldn't
sit in classrooms and stay focused on
what they were telling me, es-
especially when I wasn't interested.
That's been like a defining quality of
my life. I'm exceptionally good
at not doing things I'm not interested
in. And I'm ex- And I'm good at when I'm
interested, but when I'm not interested,
I could see my peers almost like will
themselves to engage in things they're
not interested in.
I'm I will I could never do that. And
I've always said I'm a remarkable
quitter. So, you think about stop going
to school, then went to university for 1
day and was like, "Nope."
Never went back after that first day.
So,
So, it's it's a very important piece of
advice for people who have ADD.
Is pick something you love, not a job
that you think you'll just make more
money in. And that's another sort of
piece of the puzzle that completely fits
with having
ADD. And as as we know,
there are problems with it,
but there are also huge benefits of it.
Your prefrontal cortex,
when it works too hard, so I imagine if
I scanned your dad, that it would be
busy, cuz he's very organized and like
collecting.
Um
but there's less creativity
that goes with the busy frontal lobes.
When there's a little bit sleepy,
you entertain all sorts of thoughts, and
you're a little less rule bound than
people whose prefrontal cortex more
active. They like rules, and they like
sameness, and they like predictability.
And
probably like some of that because I
think you inherited some of your dad.
That's the top of the diamond.
But
you're obviously very creative.
Mhm.
I do um I do think of myself as being um
a a
creative entrepreneur. I I know other
entrepreneurs that are like really good
at finance and operations and processes,
whereas my skill in entrepreneurship has
always been
the creativity. That's why I'm a
marketeer. That's where I built my my
fortunes, per se, was in marketing and
creativity. So
and I've always found other people to do
the
finance or the process or operation
stuff for me because that's not where I
I'm engaged or or where I think I'm
particularly good.
So
Well, and since a lot of CEOs listen to
this podcast, a lot of CEOs have ADD of
one form or another.
And they thrive
when they hire people
who are organized.
So it's very important cuz we tend to
like to hire people like ourselves.
And it's very important to hire people
who help us where we're more vulnerable.
It's almost like hiring people with
different brains. Yes. Literally.
Yes.
We we we talked about something a second
ago. You said, "When you saw your brain
for the first time, it changed your
life." I do feel like that now. I do
feel like when
I almost didn't realize my brain was
there. And I think a lot of people we go
through our lives just kind of cuz we
never see the thing.
We don't appreciate the thing. So step
one is that awareness and then step two
is the realization that we can do
something about it. Because I grew up
thinking that your brain and your body
generally is just it just is what it is.
Like I can't do anything about, you
know, I tend to think I can't do
anything about, I don't know, my
fingernail. I probably I mean you can,
but you just see these things as static
objects that are what they are.
This idea that I can do something about
it is the most important idea. It's the
it's the empowering idea.
And that is what you're telling me
is possible. I can change my brain.
It's the most exciting lesson that I've
learned. You're not stuck.
I'm not stuck
with the brain I had. You're not stuck
with the brain you have. You can make it
better. I can prove it. In fact, every
day, what I've come to believe, you're
making your brain better
or you're making it worse. Let's start
there.
you're doing. What things make the brain
worse? What are the common things that
most of us do without thinking that make
the brain worse?
When my daughter, Chloe, was in second
grade, I went to her classroom and I
wrote 20 things on the board.
And I went separate them for me. Good
for your brain, bad for your brain.
7-year-olds.
They got 19 out of 20 right. So, most
people know.
The only thing they got wrong was orange
juice.
They put it in the healthy category.
When, in fact, when is it rational to
unwrap fruit sugar from its fiber
source? Because it turns toxic in your
body. So, I'm not a fan of fruit juice.
I'm a fan of fruit, not fruit juice. But
so, the bad category. Hitting a soccer
ball with your head. No, don't do that.
Um
What's bad about sugar
for the brain?
Which What does that mean?
It makes you diabetic. But I mean as it
relates to the brain, why is like orange
juice or the ice cream bad for my brain?
Because it's ultimately going to give
you high blood sugar levels, Mhm. which
erode your blood vessels,
and you're going to have lower blood
flow to your brain.
That's bad. It's a bad thing. I mean,
there's so many things about it. So,
it's addictive, it's pro-inflammatory,
it makes it more likely you're going to
have diabetes and obesity. So, 72% of
Americans are overweight, 42% are obese.
I've published three studies on 35,000
people.
As your weight goes up, the actual
physical size and function of your brain
goes down.
That should scare the fat off anyone. I
used to be chubby, but when I figured
out that connection, I'm like, "Oh, no.
I am
It was that that gave me the motivation
to drop about 25 lb. And
so, sugar
is the gateway drug to diabetes and
obesity.
And so,
not to mention
inflammation,
which is the cause of depression and
dementia. So, I've got sugar, I've got a
head injury.
I'm going to avoid both of these things.
What else should I avoid? And then you
have low blood flow in those two very
important areas.
And so,
how can we increase blood flow? So, you
want to avoid things that cause low
blood flow, caffeine, nicotine.
Caffeine? Caffeine constricts blood flow
to the brain. What does that do to my
brain?
It Well, constricts blood flow. So,
you're going to get less blood flow. And
remember, I showed you that progression
with age?
No, you don't want that. You want to do
things that increase blood flow to your
brain. So, exercise. Um
ginkgo is just one of the supplements
I'm going to give you. Eat foods like um
beets, oregano,
rosemary, cinnamon, they increase blood
flow.
And do you think there's a correlation
or link between
caffeine
consumption and a shrinking brain?
Yes.
And a shrinking brain, is that
associated with things like dementia?
Aging brain.
I You know, I don't think there's a
connection. I haven't read any research
that says there's a connection between
caffeine
and dementia.
There's a connection with sleep
problems, and there's connection with
sleep problems and dementia. Mhm. I
think if you have like 100 mg a day of
caffeine, it's probably fine.
But, one venti
Starbucks coffee has got 330 mg of
caffeine.
Jesus.
And people just aren't thinking about
the level of caffeine they're having in
our society. What are the other very
obvious things that are not good for my
brain? Cuz I really want to make sure
that I avoid those things. So, I've got
sugar,
So, and erectile dysfunction. I mean,
while we're at So, B is for blood flow,
right? While we're on blood flow,
40% of 40-year-olds
have erectile dysfunction.
70% of 70-year-olds have erectile
dysfunction. What that means, if you
have blood flow problems anywhere, it
means they're everywhere.
And so
like no.
And
it means either you're too sedentary,
you're overweight, you're
smoking,
or having too much caffeine,
or using marijuana cuz marijuana lowers
blood flow to the brain.
And so just in that one of the 11,
it's exercise,
ginkgo.
For you, not for everybody, but for you
hyperbaric oxygen, those three things
will make a big difference in blood
flow. Ginkgo? Ginkgo. What is that? It's
a supplement. What does it do? Uh
increases blood flow. To the brain? The
prettiest brains I've ever seen take
ginkgo. There's actually SPECT study.
Uh they gave
people 100
20 mg of ginkgo twice a day, significant
improvement in blood flow to the brain.
And so in one of the supplements I'm
going to give you,
we have ginkgo.
I I've taken it every day for the last
20 years,
at least. And then this is where the US
government got an F for the pandemic,
loneliness accelerates dementia
and brain problems.
And so when they isolated us, the whole
significant increase in brain problems.
So get connected to other people.
The I in bright minds is inflammation.
So what increases inflammation? Low
omega-3 fatty acid levels. And we are
deficient.
93% of the population is deficient in
omega-3 fatty acids. 93%.
So all of us should be either eating
more fish or
taking an omega-3 supplement like fish
oil.
Gum disease. Like who knew?
Like I wasn't really that good at taking
care of my gums until I started reading
the studies. You have gum disease, you
have inflammation, you're more likely
get depressed and have dementia. I'm
like, "Oh my goodness." So, I'm a
flossing
fool.
Um
ages, head trauma, we talked about that.
I did the big NFL study when the NFL was
struggling with the truth on traumatic
brain injury in football.
80% of our players got better.
T is toxins.
Um
drugs, alcohol.
Um but other things like
mercury and
What are the unobvious toxins? Because
Anesthesia. Anesthesia. I I was looking
at my bathroom
items. And I have like mouthwash and
toothpaste and deodorants and
aftershaves. And I was wondering to
myself whether those were toxic to some
degree.
So, there's an app. There's a couple of
them, but the one I like is called Think
Dirty. Mhm. Where you can scan those
products and it'll tell you on a scale
of 0 to 10
how bad they are for you. So, 0 is you
live a long time and 10 is you die
early.
And so, when I figured this out, I was
scanning everything.
Um I mean, it cost me hundreds of
dollars to replace things.
And my wife
more than that with all the makeup and
stuff. But I shaved for 50 years with
Barbasol.
And it's a nine.
Which is die early.
And now I shave with something called
Kiss My Face. And it's a two.
It's like, you know, we teach people
read the labels on food stuff, should
read the labels on anything that goes on
your body or on your child's body. And
we have this epidemic, and we'll get to
it, of low testosterone in males because
of the toxins we put on their bodies
when they're young.
What is the M in bright?
So, the M is mental health. It's
the quality of your thoughts,
the level of your stress,
and
the level of trauma you carry
in your body.
And whether or not you have any of the
psychiatric
stuff. Like depression, for example,
doubles the risk of Alzheimer's disease
in women and quadruples it in men.
And so, the M is what's going on
in your mind.
And so, I teach people to kill the ants,
the automatic negative thoughts that
steal their happiness.
Um
understand
and process their traumas,
and treat
whatever
psychiatric issues may be present. Like
in your case,
the ADD.
And I think cuz start with the
supplement, um
or even consider medication.
Talk about the natural ways to do it,
the medicine ways to do it. And for me,
I'm not opposed to medicine. I'm
actually really good at it.
But it's never the first and the only
thing I think about. I've really never
taken medication in my life. Even like
if I get a headache, I don't take
medication. I'm not the type of person.
I probably haven't taken a pill in like
really in years. The only time I've
taken medication is if I have a severe
infection of sorts. So like there was
this one time where like my foot was
going green and I'd stood on some glass,
whatever, and it was really getting out
of control. I'm talking like a 2-in
purple thing growing on my foot. I
thought, "Okay, instead of getting my
leg cut off, I'll take this medication
the doctor's given me. Otherwise, I just
do not take it."
So I would rather go through severe pain
than take medication because I believe
that my body can fix things. Um
So when I think about taking ADD
medication or ADHD medication, I don't
really know the difference,
I go, "Well,
if my
if I'm messy or if I'm my handwriting's
bad or whatever it might be,
then that's just who I am.
And that's okay. I can get better at it.
I can be less I can be more organized.
But why why do I want to take
medication?
Well, I'm not going to I'm not going to
be the one to sell you on medication,
but what I would say
is
So a lot of times people ask me the side
effects of medication. Mhm.
And for stimulants for ADD, it could be
it decreases your appetite or can
negatively affect your sleep.
But you always have to ask the second
question.
Which is what are the side effects of
not taking
the medicine?
What's the impact
on your life, on your business, on your
money, on your relationships, on your
health? Because living with untreated
ADD for many people, and maybe not you,
but for many people goes with chronic
stress
because of
the
negative things that tend to go along
with it. Dysfunction.
And for you, you're
clearly not broken.
But are you optimized?
Do you have full access
to your own brain?
And I would argue no.
And we can do and we can do better.
But we can do it in steps.
And ultimately, I see my job
is giving people options.
And then telling them the pros and cons
of each option, and then letting them
choose. Right? I mean, that's what good
doctors should do. It's called informed
consent.
Um
and you know, I can just tell you
my experience. I told you the story with
my daughter.
And
I've seen that play out thousands of
times.
That
people
just become more optimized. In what way?
not necessarily the medicine. But that
medicine, when it's for the right brain,
right? The wrong brain, it makes people
worse. And if you read my book, Healing
ADD, I talk about the Ring of Fire ADD.
So, ADD and ADHD
are different terms for the same thing.
1980, the American Psychiatric
Association's DSM
Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of
Mental Disorders, I hate that, but
it's what we have, was Attention Deficit
Disorder, ADD, with or without
hyperactivity.
1987, God knows for what reason, they
changed the name to ADHD. Attention
Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder,
basically throwing out half the people
who had it. Cuz half the people who have
ADD or ADHD are never hyperactive. And
they don't get diagnosed because they
don't bring enough negative attention to
themselves for parents to go,
"You have a problem.
And you're giving me a problem."
Um
so, anyways, different
names for the same thing.
And if you can
manage it
by having extra help for the things
you're not good at,
with exercise,
with all of the good habits you have,
well,
that's awesome.
If you want to be be 10%
more focused, like I treat this writer,
um
and she only takes medicine when she has
to get stuff done. But she never takes
it when she writes because she has 16
plot lines going on at once in her
books. And she goes, "No, I think it
decreases my creativity a little bit."
Interesting.
Because the
the fact that we're medicating
the a brain like mine,
I
I go, "Is that for professional
optimization?" Cuz if you just go back
like, I don't know, a couple hundred
years. You go back even further to a a
time when we couldn't like read or
write, there wasn't computers, and all
of these things, you would have had no
idea that You know, if you go if you go
back far, you wouldn't have been able to
tell a
really a an ADHD Well, what I'm trying
to say
But you'd be able to tell their life. I
mean, I have a patient from Ethiopia.
And
I'm like, "So, tell me the impact in
your culture."
And he said, "The people with severe
ADHD get excluded because they can't be
relied on.
And the isolation causes great shame and
pain.
Um and
they have no idea it's a brain thing.
Where does it come from ADHD?
Or ADD?
Well, it's genetic. Okay.
It's clearly genetic. I mean, I if I
don't see it in someone's family, I
think head trauma.
And with you, I think that's possible
because of soccer. Um except you see it
in your family.
Um
Is it a defect or is it a difference?
It's a difference.
If I if I chose to take a drug, was it
like equal to Ritalin that you called it
one of the So, Ritalin would be one of
the options. Whatever drug it was, what
exactly would it do under brain scanning
to my brain? So, if I scan my brain and
took the drug, what would you see in my
brain?
Well, I can tell you. It would activate
your cerebellum. Okay, the bit that was
a bit sleepy. It was a bit sleepy and it
would activate your prefrontal cortex.
And
um
it would give your brain better energy.
So, my first SPECT scan, 1991, a woman
she tried to kill herself the night
before. I went to the lecture on brain
SPECT imaging and then I walked out of
the lecture and she was my new patient.
Her name was Sandy. She tried to kill
herself the night before and as I'm
getting to know her, I'm thinking she
has ADD. She has an 8-year-old son who
has ADD, talked about the genetic
connection. She had an IQ of 144
but never finished college. And I'm
like, "How did you study?" She said,
"Well, I never really did except maybe
the night before a test, I'd put on a
pot of coffee,
stay up all night cramming and then I'd
take the test. That's classic ADD way of
doing things.
And I'm like, "You know, I think maybe
you have adult ADD. And she goes, "Oh,
adults don't have ADD."
And I'm thinking, I'm the doctor,
I'm like, "How about if we look at your
brain?"
And And I knew from other work I'd done
that I should do it twice, at rest and
concentration.
And
when she tried to concentrate, her brain
completely deactivated.
Turned off. Like, for you, we only did
it once, but if I had done it twice,
probably your brain would be busier at
rest, and then when you try to do it, it
would drop.
And I put the pictures on
a couple of days later, I put the
picture on the table in front of her.
And as I explained it to her,
she started to cry.
And she said, "You mean it's not my
fault."
And I said, "Having ADD is sort of like
people who need glasses." And I wore
glasses to drive, and took my glasses
out, put them on.
And I said, "People who wear glasses
aren't dumb, crazy, or stupid. Their
eyeballs are shaped funny, and we wear
glasses to focus."
I said, "People with ADD aren't dumb,
crazy, or stupid. Some are among the
brightest people I know,
but their frontal lobes deactivate.
Taking the medicine is like glasses for
your frontal lobes, help you focus."
And she did it. She was conflict-driven.
She was always poking her husband. They
got into a huge fight, which is why she
tried to kill herself. She stopped that.
She's a better mom. She went back and
finished college. I mean, her life's
It's like your brain with glasses. Wow.
My friends that take medication for ADD
say that to me. They say it's like their
life is before and after that moment.
So, I've, you know, I've
I completely believe what you're saying.
Um
A second ago, you said this phrase when
we were talking about the M, which is
your mental health, and the impact that
has on the
development of a brain that's either
healthy or unhealthy. And you said this
thing about you got to make sure you
kill the ants,
which is killing those negative
thoughts. Um that's much easier said
than done.
How does How does someone go about
killing their negative thoughts? Is
there a process they can go through to
do that? Yeah, it's a habit.
Right? And it's not hard.
But like any habit, you have to do it
repeatedly, like over and over and over
and over and over and over. Um
Whenever you have a thought,
your brain releases chemicals.
Whenever you have a bad thought, a sad
thought, a mad thought, your brain
releases a certain set of chemicals that
make you feel bad.
Immediately.
Your hands get cold. They start to
sweat. Your muscles get tense. You start
to breathe erratically.
And it all happens
instantaneously.
Whenever you have a positive thought, a
happy thought, a hopeful thought,
a loving thought, like I'm back cuz I
loved the first time I was on the
podcast with you.
Um
a completely different set of chemicals
come out. And your hands get warmer,
drier. Your breathing slows down. Your
heart beats in a healthier It happens
like immediately.
People have ADD, since we're talking
about that, they tend to go more toward
negative thoughts cuz negative thoughts
are more stimulating.
And
uh
here's the exercise.
Whenever you feel sad, or mad, or
nervous, or out of control, write down
what you're thinking.
And then ask yourself, is it true?
Is it absolutely true? This is a process
I learned from my friend Byron Katie.
How do I feel when I have this thought?
How do I act when I have this thought?
And what's the outcome
of the thought? So, is it true?
Is it absolutely true?
How do I feel, act, and the outcome of
the thought?
How would I feel
if I didn't have the thought?
How would I act if I didn't have the
thought? What's the outcome of not
having that thought? Then my favorite
part of it is take the original thought,
"Tana never listens to me." Tana is my
wife. I've had that thought.
Um
and then turn it to the opposite. Tana
does listen to me.
And then just ask yourself whether or
not that's true.
And by directing my thoughts, by
managing, so rather than being a victim,
so many of my patients are victims of
their thoughts until they do the work,
right? This is one of the things where
do what the F I say.
Write down 100 of your worst thoughts.
Take them through that process.
And by the time you get to 30, they'll
stop bothering you.
So, if I'm a repetitive negative thinker
or a repetitive positive thinker, does
that alone change the shape of my brain?
Yes.
And in
my new book, Change Your Brain Every
Day, there's actually pictures of Noelle
Nelson. She was writing a book called
The Power of Appreciation.
And I had her
she wanted me to scan her while she was
appreciating her brain, and it looked
beautiful.
And I'm like, as I'm showing it to her,
I'm like, "You need to come back
tomorrow, and I want you to hate
yourself."
And she goes, "Oh, I don't want to do
that." I'm like, "Come on, you have to
suffer for science." I said, "We want to
We have positive scan, and then we have
negative scan."
And the negativity
dropped
her left temporal lobe, her left frontal
lobe, and her cerebellum.
So interesting. I mean, similar to what
your scan looks like, but hers was way
worse. I mean, this is healthy brain and
then a deactivated brain. And that
explained to me
athletic slumps.
It's like, why do people get in athletic
slumps? Cuz negativity turns off their
cerebellum. And they become just a
little less coordinated.
Interesting.
And I'm not a fan of positive thinking.
I'm a fan of accurate
thinking with a positive spin. So,
positive thinking is I can have this
third piece of cheesecake and it's not
going to negatively impact my body or my
brain.
Like, no.
The don't worry, be happy people die the
earliest
of accidents and preventable illnesses.
So,
a lot of people come to me for anxiety.
And I'm like, so, on a scale of 0 to
100, how much is it?
And they're like, 50.
I said, okay, our goal is not zero.
Our goal is 15.
I want you to have enough anxiety you do
the right things.
Somewhat linked to that is a word you
used as well, which is stress.
When we're talking about the M in bright
minds, how to have healthy brains,
what role does stress play on our
brains?
Stress,
um, especially chronic unremitting
stress. So, if we think of the stress
you had growing up,
um, where there was a lot of fighting,
it raises a hormone called cortisol.
Cortisol begins to shrink
activity in the hippocampus, one of the
major memory and learning centers in the
brain. So, one
could at least argue or postulate your
struggle in school
was because your emotional brain was
busy cuz you were worried about things
at home.
Um it makes it more likely you get
infections. It makes it
more likely um
that you have learning problems.
And trauma. Trauma was the other word
you used which I I thought it was worth
diving into. Um the impact that trauma
has on our brains.
Um and does trauma show up when you scan
someone's brain? Can you see it?
Yeah, so trauma shows up as that diamond
pattern, uh which is why I asked asked
you about it. It's your emotional brain
anterior cingulate at the top. It's the
brain's gearshift, thalamus often
involved in mood, basal ganglia,
amygdala involved in anxiety. So, we
often see worry, anxiety, and sadness.
And it shows up as that diamond pattern.
But after people do EMDR, a specific
psychological treatment for trauma,
calms it down. And I say psychological
treatment, I'm like, "Yeah, but it has
biological effects." Uh
it's a very
interesting treatment. So, I get you to
like first thing,
write down 10 big traumas
in your life. And we'll go after the
worst one first.
Um and have you bring it up. And there's
a whole process to it. But have your
eyes go back and forth while you bring
it up. And it's so interesting the
connections your brain will make to it.
But as you process it, you find you're
actually less bothered
by it. And it's masterful for single
incident traumas like being robbed or
being in a car accident. For chronic
trauma, it takes longer.
Um
but it's so helpful. Um when I met my
wife
18 years ago, um
her ACE score, adverse childhood
experiences, on a scale of 0 to 10, how
many bad things happened to you, was an
eight.
And
I was so taken with this woman. And one
of my first gifts to her was 10 sessions
of EMDR. One, I wanted to see if she
would like wrestle with her traumas. But
she went for 2 years. And I'm absolutely
convinced that's one of the reasons she
and I rarely fuss
with each other.
Because we don't trigger each other.
And when you talk about trauma, it's not
these big T traumas that some people
sometimes talk of, which is
you know, when I was young, I was
fondled by my uncle, for example. It can
also be an isolated incident that
happened when you were an adult.
Absolutely.
It can be anything that attacks
your sense of safety, either physical
or emotional.
Getting fired is traumatic for a lot of
people. Um not performing in a high
in an important situation can be
traumatic.
And that changes the activity within
your brain.
On Well, it depends on how strong it is.
If it was really strong. If it was
really strong. Then the activity centers
of your brain would
Well, and there's one thing we haven't
talked about yet called brain reserve,
which is how healthy was the brain that
you brought into trauma.
Because you can take
two soldiers,
put them in the same tank, and expose
them to the same blast, the same angles,
everything is the same. One walks away
unharmed. The other one's permanently
disabled. Why?
It's the brain they brought into
the trauma.
And so,
if your mother used drugs while she was
pregnant with you, she decreased your
reserve. If your mom and dad fought a
lot or they separated when she was
pregnant with you, that decreased your
reserve. If she gave you bad food, if
she neglected you, if there was chronic
stress, that's decreasing
your reserve. So, all of us have a
certain level of reserve when we go into
that trauma. And some people get
post-traumatic growth that they're
actually better after the trauma. You
know, they
make the trauma and makes something
meaningful out of it. And other people
have post-traumatic stress where it
really
um causes them to suffer.
I love the idea of brain reserve cuz I'm
like always thinking of boosting mine.
Yeah, because then also when something
traumatic happens, I'm in a better
place, right? Right. Like if you kill
the ants, like if your ant population is
low, my automatic negative thoughts.
Right. Yeah. So, if you're masterful, if
you have an anteater running around in
your head cleaning up the negative
thoughts that all of us have,
when you go into that trauma,
well, you're just better able to deal
with it than
if you have an undisciplined
mind that's infested.
And there's nowhere in school
that people teach you to kill the ants.
We have a foundation called the Change
Your Brain Foundation.
And I love it so much.
Uh we're dedicated to research,
education, service.
But last year we produced this new
course called Brain Thrive by Five. So
it's for preschoolers, kindergarten,
grade one,
where we teach kids to love and care for
their brain. It's like 30 modules,
they're 6 to 7 minutes long, and six of
them are on learning to kill the ants.
Uh, little kids just love that. You
don't have to believe every stupid thing
you think. And I don't know if you know,
but Jerry Seinfeld once said, "The brain
is a sneaky organ." We all have weird,
crazy, stupid, sexual, violent thoughts
that nobody should ever hear. And just
because you have bad thought doesn't
even mean you believe the thought,
right? It's not the thoughts you have
that make you suffer, it's the thoughts
you attach to
that make you suffer. I get all sorts of
crazy thoughts and I'm like,
"My brain is so creative." But I don't
believe most of them.
Quick one. Just want to talk to you
about our sponsor super quick called
LinkedIn Jobs. Hiring is one of the most
important steps in your business, and
without good people, there is literally
no company. Trust me, I found out along
the way that your business is nothing
without good people. You want to be 100%
certain that you have access to the best
candidates available, and that's why I
need you to check out LinkedIn Jobs.
LinkedIn Jobs helps you to find the
right people for your team faster and
for free. So when I'm expanding any of
my teams in any of my companies, I go
straight to LinkedIn, and I'd highly
recommend you do the same. There are
simple tools like screening questions,
which make it easy to focus on
candidates with the right skills and
experience, so you can quickly
prioritize who you'd like to interview
and hire. It's why small businesses rate
LinkedIn Jobs number one in delivering
quality hires versus leading
competitors. LinkedIn Jobs helps you
find the qualified candidates you want
to talk to faster. Post your job for
free at linkedin.com/doac.
That's linkedin.com/doac
to post your job for free. Terms and
conditions apply.
As you'll know, this podcast is
sponsored by Huel. One of my favorite
products that they've ever created is
their Huel Daily Greens. It actually
performed so well when we released it
that it sold out completely and the next
thing I'm back to here to say to you
guys is that it's now back in stock.
It tastes amazing and it's actually got
91 vitamins and minerals and whole food
ingredients in one scoop. It's nice not
to have to think about taking lots of
different pills and vitamins in the
morning. I can just take this and I know
that I'm giving my body a good dose of
all the vitamins and minerals that it
needs every morning. It's a lot better
tasting than having to force down some
of the other green powders I've tried
and it's really reassuring to know that
I'm looking after my body properly.
Unfortunately and currently, this
product is only available in the US. So,
anyone in the USA head to huel.com to
get it before it runs out again. But,
anyone that's not in the US and wants it
to come to their country, please send me
a DM, a direct message and I'll speak to
the team at Huel in our board meetings
and I'll let them know that you want it
in your country.
Tell me about the most unhealthy brain
you've ever seen.
For a 15-year-old was Kip Kinkel.
He's a 15-year-old boy in Springfield,
Oregon who brought weapons to school,
got arrested, his parents picked him up
from jail,
and sometime between 6:00 that night and
8:00 the next morning, he murdered his
mom and dad.
And then he went to Springfield Thurston
High School in Springfield, Oregon and
shot 25 people.
Based on my work, they scanned him for
his trial.
His brain was so awful. Like, I'd never
seen a 15-year-old
that had a brain so damaged.
And his life reflected it.
What did you see in his brain? It was
shriveled.
At 15? At 15.
And it's like, okay, why? Well, he
murdered his mom and dad, so I couldn't
get a good history. But he either had
anoxia
at birth, lack of oxygen, a severe
infection, or something was poisoning
his brain. It could have been lead. It
um
could have been an infection. I mean
we're talking about M, the I is immunity
and infections. It's a major cause of
psychiatric problems. Nobody knows about
it.
Have you scanned the brains of lots of
psychopaths? I have.
And what do you see when you look at a
psychopath's
So I published a study on murderers, and
young murderers have really low frontal
lobe function. Older murderers, it's
global low activity. Now, not all
murderers are the same. I have one
murderer's brain Her brain actually
looked pretty good. But she was in the
middle of being abused by her husband,
and she
murdered him. And
it wasn't that irrational, you know,
when you really know her story.
Um but most brains are
troubled.
Do you think you could look at a brain
and predict Now you should ask me,
should you scan presidential candidates?
Interesting.
Especially now. Uh
What do you think Donald Trump's brain
looks like?
Well, I think if we scanned
President Biden or former President
Trump, neither one of them would be
healthy.
I mean, one, we talked about the older
you got,
the less healthy they are, and
um
if someone is going to have nuclear
codes,
shouldn't we know what their brain looks
like?
And I wrote an op-ed piece in 2008 when
Barack Obama was running against John
McCain arguing for don't you think we
should scan presidential candidates?
And
yeah, I don't think either one of their
brains would be healthy and that
concerns me.
Because I mean, what do we need for our
top politicians?
Judgment,
forethought,
impulse control. Okay, so playing
devil's advocate to that. If we started
to do that at the very highest office in
the land, then that philosophy might
creep down to lower offices in the land
and when you go and try and get a job at
I don't know, a restaurant or a
marketing agency, it might become the
norm that there's a almost brain
discrimination or brain prejudice in
play where someone like me, they have
their brain scanned, they go, "Listen,
this guy's
he's not going to be very good at I
don't know, focusing on things like
that."
interesting question.
I have to tell you if you date one of my
children
for more than 4 months,
I'm going to get you scanned. Really?
I'm going to figure out how to do that.
It's the rule in my family.
Um and if you have a bad brain, it
doesn't mean you can't come back.
But are you smart enough to fix it?
That would be the question. Have you
done that?
Well, my son-in-law,
Jesse, who I love, his mother has
paranoid schizophrenia.
And I'm like,
"I want to scan your brain." And I have.
He actually wrote a book called Change
Your Brain Before 25 and
he opens the book with the story of his
scan and him sitting with me. He's 6'4,
I'm 5'6, and he said he'd never felt so
small.
And
Yeah, no, that's the rule in my family.
I like I said when I met my wife, I
really liked her. And the first naked
part of her I wanted to see was her
brain.
And so 3 weeks into our relationship,
I'm like, "Hey, you haven't seen the
clinic. Don't you want to see the
clinic?" She came, I scanned her, and
it passed.
Do you use her brain
against her?
I bet you do.
I bet you do. No.
We spoke to Tana, she said you do.
You're telling me there's not been one
time where you've brought up her brain
in a moment of conflict or arguments.
Not once, cuz I will call Tana.
I I don't. Yeah. No, okay.
Because you know what I do? And this is
this is on par with killing the ants.
I do an exercise with my patients called
the one-page miracle.
On one piece of paper, write down what
you want.
Relate and in a very specific way.
What do you want in your relationships?
Your work, your money, your physical,
emotional, and spiritual health. What do
you want?
And with her, cuz she's on the top of my
list, I want a kind, caring, loving,
supportive, passionate relationship. I
always want that.
I don't always feel like that. Rude
thoughts come into my head.
And if I've slept and I've eaten,
I never say them.
Why? Cuz it doesn't get me what I want.
Mhm. Right? And that's not selfish.
People go, "Oh, but you know,
what you want What what I want is not
selfish.
It's good.
Cuz hedonism is the enemy of happiness.
But happiness is a moral obligation
because of how you impact other people.
Your brain's so smart, but you have to
tell it what you
want. And every major business,
including mine, we have a one-page
strategic plan. We know what we want,
and we know what we're going to do this
quarter and this year.
But people don't do that in their lives.
And you think they should have like a
life plan? Every
person should. What do you want?
Is your behavior getting you
what you want? Do you think the brain
almost conspires to make
to fit what you want? I either brain,
once you're clear on what you want, I
guess your actions will change a little
bit, and then your brain will change
shape to fit what you've said you
wanted. Yes. And the brain is lazy.
The brain
does what you allow it to do.
And it's habitual. I was talking to one
of my patients about this yesterday.
Um
cuz we were working on his one-page
miracle.
And he's like, "You know, I could be
more positive."
And I go, "It's a habit
to be negative or to be positive. Which
highways are you building in your brain?
Positive highways or negative highways?
Accurate highways or distorted highways?
You build that."
And if you watch the news, they'll
become more distorted.
Cuz it's Yeah. In my book, The End of
Mental Illness, I I did something It was
very fun for me to do. I imagined if I
was an evil ruler
and I wanted to create mental illness,
what would I do?
And watching the news, I think it was
there's 62 evil ruler strategies and I
think that's like 12. Um, because
the news is no longer the news.
The news is about eyeballs and selling
things.
And
negativity sells. If I can scare you,
that will sell.
And so, um
you have to be very careful with what
you allow in your brain. And yes, you
should be informed.
But not over and over and over and over
again. People who start the day with the
news
are 27%
less happy in the afternoon.
Well, I listen to lots of true crime and
serial killer things.
Like every day.
Are you telling me
funny. I have this show on Instagram
called Scan My Brain. I take influential
people and scan them and I did Meghan
Trainor, uh, the
uh, musician. I love her music. And she
goes, "I can't sleep." And every night
before bed, she's listening to true
crime. And I'm like, "Stop that." Do you
think it matters? Cuz I listen to true
crime before bed.
I have this exercise that I recommend
all my patients. I've done it for
10 years.
What went well when I go to bed.
I start at the beginning of the day
and
just go hour by hour looking for what
went right about my day. I think that's
set your dreams up to be more positive.
I think it's
I do both and then I just see which one
works better for you. Every day win or
learn.
What is the I in Bright Minds? Immunity
and infections. So, do you know your
vitamin D level? No, but I do take the
only supplement that I
take frequently, I'd say there's two, is
vitamin D and omega-3.
But I've because I'm black as well, I
was You need more vitamin D. Yeah.
So,
uh people have darker skin need and
going from Africa, where there's a lot
of sun, to the UK, where there's no sun,
dramatically increase the risk of mental
health problems. Yeah.
Because of vitamin D deficiencies. Do
you know what? I think there's a certain
member of my family, who I won't name,
who went from Africa, they're
they've got two Nigerian parents, went
from Africa to the UK,
and I saw their mental health
deteriorate quite significantly to the
point that we believe this person might
have bipolar now.
And I I I
part of me suspects, once I learned
about vitamin D deficiency in people
that have darker skin,
this person has very, very, very, very
black skin, um that it might be
associated with that change.
Being in a new country that has no
sunlight for 30 years when you're,
you know, black black. You bet. Yeah.
And it's part of So, if you see
mental health is brain health, then that
becomes a critical intervention. If
you're not paying attention to brain
health, then you're like, well, what
antipsychotic or what mood stabilizer
can
I give them. And I'm fair well, may use
an antipsychotic or a mood stabilizer,
but if I get your brain healthy,
you might not need it, or you'll need
half the dose.
So, and and then infections, I mean,
we're just coming out of a pandemic,
and COVID changes your brain in a bad
way. It causes, um
like a a
inflammatory bomb to go off in your
brain.
I was on the Kardashian show last year
because I scanned Kendall. Kendall came
to see me.
And obviously I was on the show, so it
was public knowledge. And it was
post-COVID, and her emotional brain just
was on fire.
Uh, and that's what we saw with COVID.
And long COVID, emotional brain is hot,
but then the cortex begins to
um
get low in activity. It's it's a bad
combination. Well, I mean, what does
that mean? It's like chronic damage. And
what does that mean if the in terms of
behavior?
What's the implications for behavior?
So, the hot
limbic brain tense anxiety
that she hadn't had. Um, if you start
damaging your cortex, then all of a
sudden you're sad, you're impulsive,
you're irritable, you
uh,
can get dark thoughts, sometimes even
suicidal thoughts.
And people got COVID, significantly
increased in dementia.
Someone who's listening to this right
now that is depressed,
clinically depressed, um
or just feels, you know, depressive
symptoms, where do you start? Let's go
to the extreme end. Someone that can't
get themselves out of bed. I sat here
with Jada Pinkett, and she told me that
she was clinically depressed, and she if
she just got to 4:00 p.m. every day, to
her that was a victory. There are lots
of people out there that are in that
situation right now.
Where do you start with those people?
What advice do you give them? Cuz I'm
sure you see a lot of them in your
practice.
It starts
with awareness. Yeah. That maybe this is
not me, maybe it's my brain. Mhm. And
then it starts with loving your brain,
and then investigating Mhm. your brain.
Cuz depression is like chest pain. So,
if you
if somebody's like had chest pain,
you're like, "Well, where would you
start?" Well, you start with an
evaluation. You wouldn't start with
drugs.
I mean, that would be like ludicrous.
You would like go, "Well, why do you
have chest pain? Why are you depressed?
You know, how's your thyroid? Right? The
person that can't get off the couch,
they
they could be hypothyroid.
Or one of my friends got depressed,
she had anemia. She had pernicious
anemia because it was a B12 deficiency.
I I wouldn't assume, "Oh, you're
depressed, take this medicine."
Depression is what it is, it's not why
it is.
And if you don't know why it is, how do
you effectively treat something? Like so
many people come to me and they go, "I
have an autoimmune disorder."
It's like, "Well, why do you have an
autoimmune disorder? Why is your body so
mad at you it's attacking itself?"
And so, Because my body's broken.
But why is your body broken?
Right? And I and I I hate the term
broken, right? The the series like the
broken brain. And it's like,
no.
It's not optimized. Let's optimize it. I
I never want my patients to think of
them as mental.
And I never want them to think of
themselves as broken. You're awesome.
So, how can I help you be maybe 10%
more awesome? People feel like their
brain is against them.
Is working against them when they're
feeling depression or those chronic
cycles of negative thinking. Why is my
brain attacking me? Why is it against
me?
So, part of it is it's not healthy and
part of it's undisciplined.
And I got to do a lecture last year for
the coaching staff of the Miami Heat.
It was so much fun for me. And I'm
really thinking a lot about elite
performance.
And I think it's just such a better
model. It's like let me help you be your
best rather than let me fix you.
And and I think someone like you, I
mean, it's like you're already awesome.
How can I make you more awesome? How can
I give you more access
to your
brain.
And it's just it's easier to sell that
than
you know, let me give you a diagnosis of
a mental illness and
then let me give you a medicine you have
to take for the rest of your life. This
is the wrong model that psychiatry is
currently operating with. Really good
for the pharmaceutical industry. Really
bad for our society. 25% of the American
population is on psychiatric drugs.
That's just horrifying.
Is Ritalin a psychiatric drug? It is.
And I'm not opposed to psychiatric
drugs. Let's be really clear. I'm
actually really good with them.
It's never the first and only thing
I think about.
What is the N in Bright Minds?
Neurohormone.
If your hormones that affect your brain,
which are all of them,
are not optimal, you're not optimal.
And the D and S?
Like if you're
um
cold when other people are not, we
should look at your thyroid. The D is
diabesity,
where you're overweight and/or have high
blood sugar. It's the most common of the
11. 72% of people are overweight. And as
your weight goes up,
you have seven of the 11 risk factors.
It lowers blood flow to the brain and
prematurely ages the brain, increases
inflammation, it stores toxins.
It's a bad thing. And then the S is
sleep.
I've got obsessed with my sleep
recently. I have my Whoop on pretty much
all the time and they're sponsor of this
podcast, I probably should say, but I'm
also like a equity shareholder in the
company. But it's become one of my
biggest obsessions in my life is waking
up in the morning and looking at how I
slept, how much deep sleep, restorative
sleep I've had, my heart rate
variability, all that stuff. I'm
obsessed with it. What does sleep do to
my brain? I guess you said earlier that
it kind of cleans it, cleans it and
refreshes it.
Well, we didn't even know that until
it's just 10 or 12 years ago where
researchers
saw that
the fluid system in your brain, it's
called the glymphatic system, doesn't
open up when you're awake, but when
you're asleep, it opens up and then sort
of cleans things, washes things. And so
for those people like me, who I thought
I was special because I could get by on
4 hours of sleep at night, I'm sort of
running around with a toxic brain or
dirty brain. And so What are these toxic
toxins? So what is it cleaning? Have you
heard of beta amyloid, which is
cluster of proteins that increases your
risk of Alzheimer's disease? So they
build up during the day,
system cleans it. But if you're not
getting good sleep, you have more of a
toxic buildup of those kinds of clumping
proteins
that are problematic for you.
Interesting.
Is there anything else people need to
know about sleep in the brain? Because I
think everybody knows sleep is
important. A lot of people struggle with
sleep. Sleep apnea triples the risk of
Alzheimer's disease. One of the big
lessons Imaging has taught me that I can
actually see the pattern for sleep apnea
on a scan and it looks like early
Alzheimer's disease.
Bilateral parietal top back part of your
brain decreases. What is sleep apnea?
Snore loudly, stop breathing at night,
chronically tired the next day. So, when
you sleep, your breathing um you have
many apneic episodes where you stop
breathing.
And so and if you're sleeping alone, you
actually might not know it because no
one's being woken up by your snoring.
Um
and even people who've been diagnosed
with it
don't treat it because they don't want
to wear the mask at night. And I'm like,
no, you have to treat it. Otherwise
the worst thing you can do for your
brain is starve it of oxygen. That's the
worst thing you can do for your brain.
So, breath work then must be quite good
for the brain.
Breath work is good for the brain.
Um one of my tiny habits, I have many of
them for brain health is the 15-second
breath.
Uh 8 seconds in, hold it for a second
and a half, 4 seconds out, hold it for a
second and a half.
Do that four times eight times, it'll
break a panic attack.
Do it on a routine basis, it'll increase
your heart rate variability.
Breath work will? Breath work.
Heart rate variability is this metric
that I think society, much of society,
has suddenly become quite obsessed with
it, including me. Me and my friends
literally have a heart rate variability
contest every morning where we like
screenshot our heart rate variability
and drop it into the chat and some of my
friends are trying to increase theirs.
One of my friends called my friend
called Ash, I mentioned him earlier on.
His has been quite low, so he's kind of
been trying to get it up.
Um I guess we're going to have to ask
two questions here, which is what is
heart variability? And the second
question is, how do I improve it in your
view? So again, you can't change what
you don't measure. And now people who
wear Apple watches or aura rings or
devices that measure it,
heart rate variability is the
beat-to-beat variability of your heart
rate. And people go, "Oh, well, my heart
rate should beat the same." Well, no.
Actually, the more variable it is, bum
bum bum bum bum bum bum
rather than bum bum bum bum bum bum.
Um, I
first heard about heart rate variability
with babies. That when a baby is being
born, they actually put a scalp monitor
on it and they look at the heart rate
variability
of the baby. And if it's very variable,
it's bouncing all over the place, well,
it's a sign of heart health. When it
flattens and becomes even, like it's
just 70,
they go get the baby because that means
the baby is in trouble. Doesn't make any
sense, does it? It's like
counterintuitive.
It's a little bit counterintuitive,
but if your heart rate variability is
low,
you have a higher risk of anxiety,
depression, and heart disease.
Dying early. I mean, there's this huge
connection between your brain health and
your heart health.
And so, meditation increases heart rate
variability, breathwork increases heart
rate variability, exercise can increase
heart rate variability, good sleep and
good sleep hygiene can increase it. Ants
decrease heart rate variability.
I stopped drinking alcohol for this very
reason. People don't know this, but I I
mean I've probably mentioned it twice
now on on air, but I quit drinking
alcohol about a month and a half ago, I
think.
And part of the reason is when I wore my
Whoop, and then I had, I don't know, one
glass of wine or two glasses or three
glasses of wine the the day before, when
I woke up the next day, my heart rate
variability was like flashing red. It
was 30, 40. Typically, on a great day,
my heart rate variability is 150, 140,
which is strong.
Really? I know this cuz I compete with
my friends. But on a day where I had a
glass of alcohol, it'd be flashing red,
and it'd be 40. Also, if I was sick, it
would be 40. Also, if I had a really
stressful, unslept day the day before,
it would also be 40. And the fact that
alcohol was causing my heart to respond
the same as a awfully stressful, unslept
day, or COVID, I thought,
[__] [__] that.
And I've So, that's part of the reason I
quit drinking alcohol.
And now that
you have brain envy?
Yeah. You're going to have a healthier
brain if you keep it away cuz alcohol
lies to us. Alcohol lies to us? Alcohol
causes damage in the brain. Really? Even
a little bit of alcohol causes damage in
the brain. It disrupts something called
white matter.
So, gray matter nerve cell bodies, white
matter nerve cell tracks. So, white
matter's the highways in your brain that
transmit information and impulses. And
even a little bit of alcohol
has been shown to disrupt the white
matter in your brain.
I don't want anything messing with the
highways in my brain.
But I love that you measured it, you
made the connection, and then you
stopped it. It's a sign of intelligent
life because you love yourself. Mhm.
Alcohol
because there's a lot of people that are
sat on the fence right now with alcohol.
They probably don't have a really bad
relationship with it. They're probably
not alcoholics, but they kind of just
they have it because society is
constructed in such a way that on a
Friday evening when the waiter comes
over and puts down the wine list, you
just go oh I'm going to go whatever.
That's who I was. I was just on the
fence. My friend, one of my best
friends, was an alcoholic. So I
understand why he quit because he had
this really dysfunctional relationship
with it that would ruin his life. I'm
the type of person that would have one
drink, two drinks, and then I'd maybe
stop. I didn't feel the need to have
three, four, seven, 19. He was
different. And also because of that
there was no adverse consequences in my
life. So when I went away with him
recently, he's writing a book on um
alcohol and alcoholism.
He was telling me about the book and I
was going I personally wouldn't read
that book because I don't feel like I
have a problem with alcohol. This was
before I quit. So I was like what I
would love from a book, this is just me
personally, is a book that made the case
to people who are kind of sat on the
fence that drink or a beer or a glass of
wine just cuz I don't know society is
constructed in such a way where it's
hard to avoid. Um but they could go for
a mocktail if someone gave them some
performance-based evidence that alcohol,
just even a little bit, that the casual
drinking actually matters.
So this is where you come in.
Doctor.
One of my biggest
uh Instagram posts was I told you so.
Um the American Cancer Society came out
and said any alcohol increases your risk
of seven different types of cancer.
And I've been talking about this for 30
years cuz I have scans and people who
drank any alcohol have lower activity
than people who don't drink at all.
And obviously alcoholics, they have
terrible looking brains.
Um
don't do that.
But, you got to ask yourself why.
And remember we talked about the
one-page miracle. What do you want?
Relationships, work, money, physical,
emotional, spiritual health. So, where
does alcohol
come in
to that? Oh, well, it helps me relax.
Well, the 15-second breath will help you
relax, but there are no side effects to
it. That will increase your heart rate
variability. Alcohol will decrease heart
rate variability and
brain function. And if it decreases
brain function, it decreases
decision-making.
As a psychiatrist,
30%, 40% of the people I see, they
initially come to my office because it's
somehow alcohol-related.
Fight with their spouse, problems with
their kids, whatever.
I'm so impressed you noticed the
difference with heart rate variability
and then you stopped. Mhm. Yeah, cuz I
I'm I'm a I'm a fences with alcohol. And
it's crazy. I And I now understand how
difficult it is to stop in our society.
I was telling my team I quit and I went
for dinner with a guy called Skrillex.
Like everyone knows Skrillex, he's a DJ,
Sonny. And this was a week after I'd
quit. Sat in the restaurant, the waiter
comes over,
bless him, and he goes, "Here's the wine
list." I go, "I I don't drink alcohol."
He goes He goes and gets a bottle of
wine
and he puts it next to me and goes,
"This is not alcohol, this is art. I'm
going to leave it next to you just in
case you get tempted." And Sonny's
Sonny, to his credit, is telling this
waiter that he doesn't drink. This
waiter is having none of it. And in that
moment,
I understood
how difficult it is to quit in the
society that we've built, where every
social interaction apparently needs to
be fueled by alcohol. And if you say no,
you're either weird or someone will try
and change your mind
or persuade you otherwise. It's just
this culture we have. It's the evil
ruler society. I think that's an evil
ruler strategy. The food pushers, the
drug pushers, the alcohol pushers. Um
For me, I just I look at people like
that and it's like, "So, why do you want
me to drink when I don't want to?"
What's it a What's going on with you?
Yeah. And I usually shut them down. Um
But,
why? An interesting question. When you
go to a restaurant, the first thing they
do is put bread on the table
and ask if you want alcohol because both
of them drop your frontal lobes.
Both of them make it more likely you're
going to order more
and spend more money at the restaurant.
So, the bread is an investment on their
part because bread gives you a sugar
spike, a blood sugar spike, which then
pushes serotonin in your brain
and makes you happy.
But, serotonin drops frontal lobe
function.
One thing they never tell you when they
give you an SSRI for depression is, "Oh,
you're going to become a little bit more
impulsive because it's going to drop
your frontal lobes."
And then alcohol, which also drops your
frontal lobes. So, you'll drop more cash
in the restaurant.
Question then, on this point of alcohol,
if I took two people
off the street, let's say they do
everything in their lives the same other
than what I'm about to say. I gave one
of them
a casual drink for the next decade. Just
maybe two drinks a week, three drinks a
week for the next decade. And the other
person was completely sober for the next
decade. When you looked at their brain
in 10 years time, if they were doing
everything the same, would you see a
difference?
Yes.
The person who is drinking two or three
times a week will have less blood flow
in their brain.
And will that have changed the shape of
their brain?
Yes, it'll be a little bit more
shriveled.
And then that means their behavior's
going to change as well.
They'll have a little bit less impulse
control. And when you look at the brain
of an A little bit less impulse control
when you're doing hard things like
marriage.
Not a good thing. Or raising children,
or managing a business. It's like
you don't want a little bit worse
decisions.
Sex.
Sex and libido. A lot of people are
struggling with their sex lives, getting
an erection, getting aroused, men and
women.
The brain and sex.
I imagine you have people come to you
and go, "Listen, me and my wife, me and
my partner, me and my husband, we've
stopped having sex. I've lost my
libido." When you hear that
and you offer people advice on libido
and sex, what is what You fix your
brain, right? Your sex life gets better.
In large part, it's about blood flow.
And if you're having erectile
dysfunction or low libido, um you got to
go, "Well, why?" Is what are the risk
factors with that? And many of them
relate to what's going on in your brain.
And I I
So often people go, "I did everything
you said and my wife's so much happier
with our sex life." Um
You have to check your hormones. I think
that's very important. You have to deal
with whatever sexual trauma might be
there.
Um the biggest sex organ in the body is
your brain.
If there's no forethought, there's no
foreplay.
And so
it's about the decisions that you make.
What else do we need to know about sex?
If I'm trying to get my partner in the
mood and I'm trying to make them
aroused.
It depends on their brain. Okay, right.
So, if your partner has a very busy
frontal lobe, that part called the
anterior cingulate gyrus,
you can't go,
"Come on, let's have sex." Because
you've met people with the automatic no,
that no matter what you say, they're
going to say the opposite of it, or
they're going to
fuss with it. I mean, it's like, "It's a
nice day today." "Oh, no, it was nicer
yesterday." I mean, even simple things.
"So, you going to want to have sex?"
"No."
Um
I was at this lecture once, and
somebody came up to me at a break and
said, "You've helped me so much.
Um I thought my wife just didn't love
me. And what I realized is that part of
her brain was just working too hard. So,
now I ask everything in the opposite."
It's like, "Oh,
like if I wanted to go to the store,
she'd never want to go with me. And I'd
go, so now what I do is I go,
'I'm going to go to the store, you
probably don't want to come.' 'What do
you mean I don't want to come? Of course
I want to come.'
He said, "But it doesn't sound right to
say, 'Well, you probably don't want to
have sex.'"
Oh, I go, "Okay, I know her brain do
this." And I gave him natural things to
boost serotonin.
So, I said,
"Take her out for a pasta dinner." So,
I'm not a fan of pasta generally, except
for these people.
Take her out for a pasta dinner, because
pasta increases serotonin. Then take her
for a walk around the lake, cuz exercise
increases serotonin. Then give her a
piece of dark chocolate. Not too many,
cuz if you get her too many, she'll have
no need for you. But
dark chocolate has PEA in it,
phenylethylamines, that'll alert your
brain that something fun is about to
happen.
And then,
put on a little baby powder, because
baby powder, it's been shown
scientifically is a natural aphrodisiac
for women cuz what do women
unconsciously associate to baby powder?
Babies. And unconsciously they want one.
And then
rub her back and don't ask for anything
directly.
And from about day 4 to about day 18 of
her menstrual cycle, you're likely to
get lucky.
Why from day 4 to day
Because she's The last week of a woman's
menstrual cycle, especially people who
have this brain type tend to be
more irritable. Is that before their
period?
Yes, it's before the period. Okay, so
the week before their period is when
she's going to be
weeks before their period is generally
the best time. Do men and women have
different brains?
Significantly?
Wildly so. Wildly different?
whole thing about you can't put your
gender on your medical forms is just
insanely stupid. Uh
because gender matters. Like estrogen
and testosterone, they matter when it
comes to brain function. I published a
study on 46,000
scans looking at the differences between
male and female brains and they're wild.
Uh women have much better frontal lobes
function, that much better blood flow to
the front part of their brain. Which
makes them Which makes them good leaders
if you think of impulse control and
collaboration and communication.
And the one statistic that just hammers
this home is who goes to jail.
Men.
14 times more than women.
But women get depressed twice as much as
men because their limbic or emotional
brain is much busier than the male
brain. And that's why in every um human
society, women are primary caretakers
for children. Um women have a bigger
nesting instinct. So I told you we moved
recently. And moving is much harder on
women in general than it is in men
because they feel like they lose their
nest and they have to redo their nest
and I was an army psychiatrist for 7
years and I used to always tell the
guys, I'm like, when you move, you stay
home and help her put the house together
cuz she's going to be way happier
uh
for you.
On that impulse control bit, I remember
reading the statistics that men
suffer with gambling addictions and
betting addictions significantly more
than women.
Drug addictions, alcohol, ADD five times
more than
women. Um
But women get help
because
they're not afraid to ask for help.
Where for men, it's often a macho thing.
It's like there's nothing the matter
with me, which is why women attempt
suicide three to four times more than
males, but males kill themselves three
to five four times more than women do
because men use more violent means. And
men aren't communicating
I'm in trouble.
Saunas. Saunas and exercise on the
brain.
Good good for the brain?
So I'm a huge fan of saunas
uh
because
of the studies mostly from
Northern Europe, people take the most
saunas have the lowest incidence of
Alzheimer's disease. And I told you
about my mercury detoxing is really
important. And you can detox in a lot of
different ways, but sauna is one of the
most effective ways.
Um
exercise is you want to stay young, walk
like you're late.
If you're 80 and you can walk 3 miles an
hour, you have a 90% chance of living
till you're 90. If you can only walk a
mile an hour, you have a 90% chance
you're not going to live until you're
90. So, exercise boosts blood flow, it
increases
uh brain-derived neurotrophic factor. It
increases serotonin, increases dopamine.
Um
another interesting thing is should you
do cold plunges? Because cold plunges
have been found to fairly dramatically
increase dopamine.
So, you should do cold plunges?
Not if you have heart problems. So, if
you have heart problems, I wouldn't do
that. But, if you have inflammation, if
you have pain, if you tend to be
depressed, there's evidence cold plunges
can be helpful.
What about weight in the brain?
When you look at someone who is
clinically obese and you look at their
brain, what do you see? And if I'm
trying to lose weight,
what do I need to know about the brain?
You know, I've thought a lot about this
because I have obesity in my family. Um
as your weight goes up,
the size and function of your brain goes
down.
And that's horrifying.
People who are in our society is against
us. I mean, you just I wrote a book
called The Brain Warrior's Way, and I
argue you're in a war for the health of
your brain. Everywhere you go, someone's
trying to shove bad food down your
throat that will kill you. I can see the
emotion in your face when you say this.
Yeah.
Uh
it's just horrifying, you know, to think
of Carl's Jr. that will take these
you know, Charlotte McKinney or
Katherine Webb, these beautiful women
and have them eat cheeseburgers and it's
unconsciously people are like, if you
eat those burgers these women will want
you. Well, these women have spit buckets
on those sets where every time they take
a bite they spit it out because they'd
never have those bodies if they ate
that food. We are being manipulated
and it is causing what I think is one of
the greatest epidemics ever
of obesity and if you're overweight
lower blood flow, aging, inflammation,
stores toxins, makes you feel awful
about yourself.
Takes healthy testosterone. We talked
about, you know, why the low. Takes
healthy testosterone and turns it into
unhealthy cancer-promoting forms of
estrogen. It's just a disaster what's
happening.
I think
you have to start counting your
calories.
And, you know, I run up against all
sorts of scientists go calories don't
count. It's complete crap.
Now, the quality of your calories is
just as important but don't eat more
than you need. And we live in a society
where we're eating way too much and
people don't know. If you think of the
Cheesecake Factory and these monster
portions, it's like, that's insane.
And it's a big thing that changed.
But the obesity epidemic really started
as the US government, among others,
demonized
fat.
Everything became low fat in the '80s.
Low fat, low cholesterol.
And
they put sugar in things to replace it.
And in fact, it just came out recently,
it was in the '60s that some of the
sugar companies paid scientists to say
it's fat, not sugar. And it damaged
millions of people.
Last thing I wanted to ask you about is
Well, there's really two outstanding
questions that I have for you, doctor.
The first one is about screen time.
People want to know,
does screen time, this generation that
have grown up 11 hours a day on a screen
or social media, up to 11 hours a day,
according to some studies,
does that have an impact on our brain?
It does. It shrinks it. It's sad. I
mean, what it does is it wears out your
pleasure centers.
So, you have these two
areas in your brain called the nucleus
accumbens, and they respond to dopamine.
And they bring you happiness, and they
bring you pleasure, and they bring you
motivation, and they bring you drive.
And
when you're hitting them
like every buzz on your phone, every
notification,
every time you scroll and you like
something, you just got a little hit of
dopamine.
Well, the more you do it, pretty soon
you thrill them to death. You begin to
wear out those pleasure centers. And you
Let's just take fame, for example. I've
been blessed to see Justin Bieber and
Miley Cyrus and a whole bunch of really
fascinating, cool people
who've been really depressed. It's like,
how can you be depressed? You're Justin
Bieber. Or how can you believe you're
not enough?
Right? Cuz their pleasure centers get
worn out by being noticed over and over
and over again. Well, when you allow
that in your brain, the screen time, 3
and 1/2 hours. If you're on for 3 and
1/2 hours
a day, you have an increased risk of
anxiety, depression, addiction, obesity,
ADHD.
And our society is on way more than
that. And you go, "So, why are we having
this epidemic
of uh
teenage suicide and mental health
problems, especially in teenage girls?"
Social media.
It's one of the big issues of the day.
And not only are you wearing out your
pleasure centers, you hate yourself
because you think everybody's better
than you are. It's the comparison dragon
that
is damaging you.
My last question is about happiness,
which we're talking about there.
I spoke to I think it was Tali Sharot
that told me happiness takes on this
kind of interesting arc through our
lives where
at the start of our lives we're a little
bit happier, then in the middle of our
lives we're a little bit sadder, and
then as we age, we go back into being
happy.
Now, I was contrasting that information
to what you said about how the brain
withers with age. If the brain is
withering with age, then how come a lot
of neuroscientists think that happiness
resembles this kind of U-shape in our
lives, where in the middle of our lives
we're less happy, and the start and the
end we're more happy?
That's a great question.
We're less striving as we age, right?
So, after 65, 70, we've sort of
done
much of the hard things that we need to
do.
And so, depression also goes up with
age, too.
And obviously, dementia goes up with
age. So,
I think it's because I don't have to
accomplish things, which makes the
middle part so
hard.
So, we're more satisfied with the nature
of our lives because we're not trying to
Well, if if we are, right? If If we're
not, then that becomes a problem and
increases the risk of depression.
It's complicated though, isn't it?
Because, you know, you get older, you
probably have less connections as well,
so that's a confounding factor and Yeah,
so I wouldn't I mean, I I ended I have
seen that research and I wrote a book on
happiness
because, you know, when I write a book,
it'll take me 6 to 9 months to write it
and I'm like, "So, what do I really want
to think about for this next 6 to 9
months?"
And I
loved it because
like
negative thinking is a bad habit,
is happiness is also a habit.
And when I go to bed and I go, "What
went well today?"
I'm feeding happiness. Or throughout the
day, if I look for the micro moments of
happiness, you know, "What's the
smallest thing that's going to happen
today that's going to make me happy?"
Then I'm just happier.
I I hear all of this and I read read all
of this in your books and one of the
things I've really taken away personally
is because I have so much information,
what I need to do is select a couple of
these habits and basically put them into
my calendar.
Like you talked about the breath work
and you talked about the gratitude
exercise at night and those kinds of
things. What I need to do is get a
couple of them and just insert them into
my calendar. Because, you know, if
they're not scheduled, they probably
won't happen in a life as busy as mine.
So, as well as making small sort of
changes to the, you know, maybe dietary
things or water or whatever it might be,
drinking a little bit less caffeine.
I've already quit alcohol. Make sure I
focus on my sleep. Some of these I want
to make routines in my life, so that's
what I'm going to do. That's what I'm
going to take away from this. We have a
closing tradition on this podcast where
the last guest leaves a question for the
next guest not knowing who they're going
to be leaving it for.
And the question that's been left for
you is quite perfect. I think.
What have you changed your mind about in
the last decade?
Well, the first thing that comes to my
mind is this idea
that I got from Dennis Prager.
Which is happiness is a moral
obligation.
I never thought of it that way.
I grew up Roman Catholic.
That idea was nowhere
in my family. It was nowhere in the
Catholic school I went to. And and I'm
grateful for my education.
Uh and I'm grateful for my faith.
But it was about should
and shaming
rather than
elevation.
And the fact that happiness is a moral
obligation.
There's this video that Dennis Prager
produced that I just love called Why Be
Happy.
And
and I never thought
that
how I feel
influences everybody around me.
That if I'm unhappy
that's not just about me. That's about
everybody I come in contact with. So
working on myself
is the most loving thing I can do
for other people.
Daniel G. Amen.
Thank you so much. Thank you for an
amazing conversation. And also thank you
for taking the time to look at my brain.
And you're totally right. Now that I
have the awareness that that brain even
exists, having seen it, it's almost like
I feel like it's like a Pablo, my dog. I
now feel a responsibility to take care
of it. And I think that that coupled
with everything that you've imparted on
me about the fact that I can do
something about it for me is
life-changing.
And you know, I could have sat here all
day and read tens of thousands of
comments that I saw online
about the work that you're doing to help
people live happier, healthier lives.
And the
consequence that has for generations, I
think, is maybe the most special thing
of all. Because if you can tilt
someone's brain in a better direction,
you're not just tilting their brain in a
better better direction, you're tilting
generations to come
of brains in a better direction. And
that alone will tilt society in a better
direction. And that's exactly the work
that you're doing. So, I know we talked
about your father last time round.
You know, often times we don't get the
praise from the our parents that I guess
we
we always longed for.
But I really hope you understand
how proud everyone is of you.
All the patience that you've
invested time and love and energy and
all the people that listen to this show
that were tilted in a better direction
because of you. And
me as well.
My life's been tilted in a better
direction because of you. So, thank you.
Thank you so much. What a joy.